<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A solemne passion of the soules loue</title>
            <title>Mary Magdalens love. Selections</title>
            <author>Breton, Nicholas, 1545?-1626?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16792</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104706</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840439</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840439</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4945</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16792)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4945)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 178:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A solemne passion of the soules loue</title>
                  <title>Mary Magdalens love. Selections</title>
                  <author>Breton, Nicholas, 1545?-1626?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Simon Stafford [in the shop of Valentine Simmes] for William Barley, and are to be solde at his shop in Gratious street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Nicholas Britten.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>A reprint of part 2 of: Mary Magdalens love.</note>
                  <note>"The types and ornaments are those of Simmes"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4945:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4945:1"/>
            <p>A Solemne Paſsion of the Soules Loue.</p>
            <p>At London Printed by Simon Stafford for William Barley, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop in Gratious ſtreet. 1598.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4945:2"/>
            <head>A ſolemne Paſsion of the Soules Loue.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>A Wake, my ſoule, out of the ſleepe of ſinne,</l>
               <l>And ſhake off ſlouth the ſubiect of thy ſhame,</l>
               <l>Search out the way how beſt thou maieſt beginne</l>
               <l>To holy worke thine humble will to frame:</l>
               <l>Then proue not weary of a little paine,</l>
               <l>When fleſhes griefe will breede the ſpirits gaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Confeſſe thy ſelfe vnworthy of the ſence,</l>
               <l>To learne the leaſt of the ſupernall will,</l>
               <l>Beſeech the heauens in ſtrength of their defence,</l>
               <l>To ſaue and keepe thee from infernall ill:</l>
               <l>Then fall to worke that all the world may ſee,</l>
               <l>The ioyfull loue betwixt thy God and thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell of his goodnes how he did create thee,</l>
               <l>And in his iuſtice, how he doth correct thee,</l>
               <l>And in his loue, how he will neuer hate thee,</l>
               <l>And that his mercy neuer will reiect thee:</l>
               <l>And how he helpt thee when the world diſtreſt thee,</l>
               <l>And with his graces how he ſweetly bleſt thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Say, I was ſicke, and he did ſend me health,</l>
               <l>I vvas in priſon, and he ſet me free,</l>
               <l>And I vvas poore, and he did ſend me wealth,</l>
               <l>And I vvas blinde, and he did make me ſee:</l>
               <l>I vvas perplext, and he did heale my paine,</l>
               <l>And being dead, he gaue me life againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhen I was lame, he did my limmes reſtore,</l>
               <l>VVhen I vvas deafe, he made me heare his voice,</l>
               <l>VVhen I vvas vvounded, he did heale my ſore,</l>
               <l>VVhen I vvas ſad, he made my ſoule reioice:</l>
               <l>VVhen I had ſind, he would not yet forſake me,</l>
               <l>VVhen I vvas loſt, he did to mercy take me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4945:2"/>
               <l>To ſay yet more, what he hath done for me,</l>
               <l>I needes muſt ſay, his goodnes hath no ende,</l>
               <l>Who, when on earth he ſaw no friend to me,</l>
               <l>Did make me feele I had a heauenly friend:</l>
               <l>A heauenly friend whoſe helpe doth faile me neuer,</l>
               <l>But is my comfort, and my king for euer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This is my Lord, my life, and all my loue,</l>
               <l>My liuing Loue, and louing life indeede,</l>
               <l>This is the bleſſing of my beſt behoue,</l>
               <l>The ſacred fruit whereon I ſweetely feede:</l>
               <l>This is the ioy that makes my heart to ſing,</l>
               <l>Honour and glory to my heauenly king.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh king more glorious than the world can know thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>From whom the day, euen from on high doth ſpring,</l>
               <l>Where glorious works vnto the world doe ſhew thee,</l>
               <l>Of glorious loue the euerliuing king:</l>
               <l>The king of life, in whom the ſoule doth proue,</l>
               <l>The higheſt glory of the heauenly Loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By whoſe high hands were all things made at firſt,</l>
               <l>By whoſe deepe wiſedome they are gouernd ſtill,</l>
               <l>By whom alone, are bleſſed or accurſt.</l>
               <l>That loue his word, or diſobay his will:</l>
               <l>By whoſe ſweete breath they liue that do attend him,</l>
               <l>And by whoſe wrath they die that doe offend him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For who can bide the fury of his yre?</l>
               <l>Or halfe conceiue the comfort of his loue?</l>
               <l>Who plagues his foes with an infernall fire,</l>
               <l>And plants his ſeruants in the heauens aboue:</l>
               <l>Who ſhakes the heauens, &amp; makes the mountains bow</l>
               <l>If he but once begin to knit the brow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And where he loues, what will he leaue to doe,</l>
               <l>To make the ſoule acquainted with his kindnes?</l>
               <l>And with what ioy will he the ſpirit wooe,</l>
               <l>To ſhun the woes that grow of worldly blindnes?</l>
               <l>What paine, or griefe, or death did he refuſe,</l>
               <l>To ſaue their liues that he did ſweetely chuſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4945:3"/>
               <l>Now for the greatnes of his glorious power,</l>
               <l>He is almighty and all glorie his,</l>
               <l>He made the yeare, the month, day, night and hower,</l>
               <l>The heauens, earth, ſea, and vvhat in them there is:</l>
               <l>In him alone doth all their being ſtand,</l>
               <l>And liue or die in his almighty hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He ſpake the vvord, and by his vvord they vvere,</l>
               <l>And all vvas good his ſecret vviſedome did,</l>
               <l>His vvill did vvorke his fauour vvithout feare,</l>
               <l>And not a thought is from his knowledge hid:</l>
               <l>He knowes the hearts, &amp; ſearcheth through the raines</l>
               <l>And ſees the roots euen of the ſmalleſt vaines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hee deckt the Skye with ſunne &amp; moone &amp; ſtarres,</l>
               <l>And made the ſeas to flowe vpon the ſand,</l>
               <l>Vpon whoſe ſhore his hand did ſet the barres,</l>
               <l>They ſhall not paſſe to ouerflowe the Land.</l>
               <l>Amid the ayre he hath diſpearſt the Clowdes,</l>
               <l>And onely man within his mercy ſhrowdes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Within the depth the fiſh their holes doe keepe,</l>
               <l>And in the rocks the Conny makes his houſe,</l>
               <l>Into the earth the crawling wormes doe creepe,</l>
               <l>And hollowe rocks are harbour for the mouſe:</l>
               <l>The Lion keepes his den, the bird his neſt,</l>
               <l>And man alone doth but in mercy reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet theſe and all are guided by his power,</l>
               <l>And may not paſſe the paſſage he hath giuen them,</l>
               <l>The ſun his courſe, the Moone muſt know her houre,</l>
               <l>And clouds muſt wander but where winds haue driuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Beaſts know their times, &amp; fiſhes know their tides,</l>
               <l>And man alone in onely mercie bides.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To tell of vvonders by his wiſedome vvrought,</l>
               <l>Euen from the greateſt to the very leaſt,</l>
               <l>Which time declares by true experience taught,</l>
               <l>In fiſh, and foule, in bird, in man and beaſt:</l>
               <l>Marke but the power, that doth in each abide,</l>
               <l>And hovve it vveakens in their higheſt pride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4945:3"/>
               <l>The Lyon firſt is fearefull of the Bee,</l>
               <l>The Elephant doth dread the little mouſe,</l>
               <l>Acrovving Cocke the Dragon may not ſee,</l>
               <l>The ſtouteſt Engle ſubiect to the louſe:</l>
               <l>The greateſt Oxe a little taint vvorme killeth,</l>
               <l>And many a man a little Canker ſpilleth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet is the Lyon feared for his force,</l>
               <l>The Elephant a huge and mighty beaſt,</l>
               <l>The fiery Dragon kills without remorſe,</l>
               <l>And Eagles carry lambes vnto their neſt:</l>
               <l>The Oxe the taint vvorme vnder foote doth tread,</l>
               <l>And man ſometimes doth kill the Cankers head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But vvhen that power begins to gather pride,</l>
               <l>Then ſee the ſtrength of the almighty hand,</l>
               <l>By vvhoſe high helpe the vveakeſt thinges are tride,</l>
               <l>To ſpoile the ſtrength vvherein the ſtrongeſt ſtand:</l>
               <l>That they may knovv there is a power on hie.</l>
               <l>In vvhom they liue, and at his pleaſure die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To ſhewe examples of the heauenly might,</l>
               <l>Againſt the pride of the inferiour power,</l>
               <l>The vvord of truth doth giue a glorious light,</l>
               <l>Where may be ſeene in minute of an houre:</l>
               <l>How greateſt ſtaies that on their ſtrength were grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</l>
               <l>With headlong fals vvere vtterly confounded.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How Pharaoh firſt, the proud Egyptian king,</l>
               <l>That vvould not ſuffer Iſrael to paſſe,</l>
               <l>What plagues and griefes did the almighty bring,</l>
               <l>Vpon the houſe, euen vvhere his lodging vvas!</l>
               <l>Frogges, flies, and lice did freely make their vvay,</l>
               <l>Euen to the chamber vvhere proud Pharaoh lay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A number plagues the Lord did further threaten,</l>
               <l>His Land vvas ſtrooken vvith a darkeſome feare,</l>
               <l>His graſſe and corne by Graſhoppers vvere eaten,</l>
               <l>The plague deſtroied his people euery vvhere:</l>
               <l>And laſt himſelfe amidſt his army crowned,</l>
               <l>Was in a moment in the red ſea drowned.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4945:4"/>
               <l>Yet through theſe ſeas his hand did make the way,</l>
               <l>Where all his ſeruants went and wet no foote,</l>
               <l>Which proues, his loue was his elected ſtay,</l>
               <l>While rebell hearts were torne vp by the roote:</l>
               <l>Which true example to the world may proue,</l>
               <l>The glorious greatnes of his power and loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Goliah boaſted greatly of his ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Yet little Dauid kild him with a ſtone,</l>
               <l>The Madian Hoaſt was ſtrong, but yet at length,</l>
               <l>By Gideons hand the kings were ouerthrowne:</l>
               <l>By change of tongues fell Babylons high tower,</l>
               <l>And Chriſt his word did breake the diuels power.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet in it ſelfe what weaker is than water,</l>
               <l>Which drownd proud Pharao with his mighty hoſt?</l>
               <l>A lowſe or flie is of a little matter,</l>
               <l>Yet with ſuch vvormes are men tormented moſt.</l>
               <l>What ſtrength alas is in a little ſtone?</l>
               <l>Yet ſo vve reade Goliah ouerthrowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Know then From whence this wonder power groweth</l>
               <l>But from the force of the almighty hand,</l>
               <l>Which to the vvorld his glorious power ſhoweth,</l>
               <l>When vvith the weake the ſtrongeſt cannot ſtand:</l>
               <l>King Dauid vvrote, and it is truely knowne,</l>
               <l>That power belongeth vnto God alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To proue the proweſſe of the heauenly power,</l>
               <l>How many more examples may be ſhowne,</l>
               <l>There is no yeare, no day, no night, nor houre,</l>
               <l>But ſome ſuch action to the vvorld is knowne:</l>
               <l>That truth may vvell vnto his glorie ſpeake,</l>
               <l>God is of power, and all the vvorld is weake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſince the vvorld cannot the bookes containe,</l>
               <l>Wherein his vvorks of vvonder may be vvrit,</l>
               <l>To admiration let his power remaine,</l>
               <l>And ſay, All powers are ſubiect vnto it:</l>
               <l>And let me of his loue and mercy write,</l>
               <l>Which is the ſubſtance of the ſoules delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4945:4"/>
               <l>This powerfull Loue, the glorie of all grace,</l>
               <l>When he had wrought the world vnto his will,</l>
               <l>And planted each thing in his proper place,</l>
               <l>And in the courſe that they continue ſtill:</l>
               <l>Of all the workes that he in wonder wrought,</l>
               <l>Made onely man the deareſt of his thought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For what he made he made but man to ſerue,</l>
               <l>And man to ſerue his onely ſacred loue,</l>
               <l>And in his loue doth ſo mans life preſerue,</l>
               <l>As may the comfort of his care approue:</l>
               <l>And ſo approue as may this ſentence giue.</l>
               <l>His onely loue doth make the ſoule to liue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He loued the earth when he did giue it life,</l>
               <l>He loued the life when he his Image gaue it,</l>
               <l>He loued the fleſh that made the bone a wife,</l>
               <l>He loued the ſoule when he from death did ſaue it:</l>
               <l>He loued him euer, yet he loued him moſt,</l>
               <l>To fetch him home when he himſelfe had loſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Come Poets, ye that fill the world with fanſies,</l>
               <l>Whoſe faining Muſes ſhew but madding fits,</l>
               <l>Which all too ſoone do fall into thoſe franzies,</l>
               <l>That are begotten by miſtaking vvits:</l>
               <l>Lay downe your liues, compare your loue vvith mine,</l>
               <l>And ſay whoſe virtue is the true diuine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For further triall let me giue you leaue,</l>
               <l>To adde a trueth vnto your idle ſtories,</l>
               <l>Wherevvith ſo oft you do the vvorld deceaue,</l>
               <l>And gaine your ſelues but ill conceited glories,</l>
               <l>Yet when you ſee vvhere ſweeteſt ſights are ſhowne,</l>
               <l>Looke on my Loue, and bluſh to ſee your owne,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With ſunny beauties let your loues be bleſt,</l>
               <l>The ſunne doth fetch his light but from my Loue,</l>
               <l>You haue your wonders from the Phoenix neſt,</l>
               <l>Mine honour liues but in the heauens aboue.</l>
               <l>Your Muſes do your Ladies praiſes ſing,</l>
               <l>The Angels ſing in glory of my King.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4945:5"/>
               <l>The earth alas, from whence your loues receiue</l>
               <l>Their floures &amp; ſweets, their pearls &amp; pretius ſtones,</l>
               <l>To decke themſelues, with which they do deceiue</l>
               <l>The blinded ſpirites of the ſimple ones:</l>
               <l>This earth from whence their outward graces ſpring,</l>
               <l>Is but the footeſtoole of my heauenly King.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And if he ſo hath deckt the earth belovv,</l>
               <l>Imagine then the glory of his ſeate,</l>
               <l>Which may perſvvade where Angels tremble ſo,</l>
               <l>For humane eies the glory is too great:</l>
               <l>For vvhere the ſun, the moone, and ſtars haue light,</l>
               <l>For natures eies the Beauty is too bright.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And vvho doth liue that euer ye did loue,</l>
               <l>But that ye could their faireſt faire vnfolde?</l>
               <l>And my faire loue, let faireſt truth approue,</l>
               <l>No eie can liue, in glory to behold:</l>
               <l>Your cleareſt beauty is vvith age declining,</l>
               <l>My Loues bright glory is for euer ſhining.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If you be vviſe, thinke vvhere true wiſedome liueth,</l>
               <l>And then allovv the honour to my loue:</l>
               <l>If yours be kinde, thinke vvho the comfort giueth,</l>
               <l>And knovv the turkey from the turtle doue:</l>
               <l>If conſtant yours, that truth let my loue trie,</l>
               <l>Who loſt his life, to ſaue his loue thereby.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And let me ſee, hovv liueth all your loue,</l>
               <l>But on deſert the ſtay of all your ſtate,</l>
               <l>And in my Loue a further life approue,</l>
               <l>Who lou de indeede vvhen he had cauſe to hate:</l>
               <l>Your fancies oft for lacke of fauour ſtarue,</l>
               <l>But my Loue doth both mine and yours preſerue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then truly ſay whom chiefe your loues doe chuſe,</l>
               <l>To caſt the countenance of their fauours on,</l>
               <l>Then vvhom againe they vvholy do refuſe,</l>
               <l>In liking thought as moſt to looke vpon:</l>
               <l>Then do but looke vpon my loue his choice,</l>
               <l>And vvhoſe heart moſt he maketh to reioyce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4945:5"/>
               <l>The vvealthy, mighty, vviſe and vvell at eaſe,</l>
               <l>Doe fit the fanſies of your Ladies beſt:</l>
               <l>But poore, and vveake, and ſimple ſoules beſt pleaſe,</l>
               <l>My heauenly Loue, to labour in his breſt:</l>
               <l>And vvho the world doth vtterly refuſe,</l>
               <l>Thoſe doth my Loue vnto his fauour chuſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſee vvhat power is in your louing natures,</l>
               <l>To take or giue vvhat ye may gaine or loſe,</l>
               <l>And ye ſhall ſee they are but my loues creatures,</l>
               <l>Whoſe liues are at his pleaſure to diſpoſe:</l>
               <l>And vvhile your fauours all doe fade away,</l>
               <l>My ſweete Loues bleſsings neuer vvill decay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Could ye conceiue the ſmalleſt of the ſweete,</l>
               <l>That doth diſcend from my ſoules deareſt Loue,</l>
               <l>Vpon the faith that falleth at his feete,</l>
               <l>That doth in prayer but his mercy proue:</l>
               <l>And you vvill blot out euery idle line,</l>
               <l>And yeeld your ſoules vnto this Loue of mine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Compare a vveede vnto a holſome flower,</l>
               <l>A cloudy euening to a ſunny daie,</l>
               <l>A foggie miſte vnto an Aprill ſhower,</l>
               <l>Nouember blaſte vnto a bloome of May:</l>
               <l>And you ſhall eaſily ſee the difference plaine,</l>
               <l>Betwixt my ſun-ſhine and your ſhowers of raine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Compare meere folly to the fineſt vvit,</l>
               <l>The courſeſt copper to the pureſt golde,</l>
               <l>The healthfull body with an ague fit,</l>
               <l>And ſet the youthfull age againſt the old:</l>
               <l>The Rauens foule note to Philomelaes voice,</l>
               <l>And quickly ſay, which is the better choice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Compare foule pride to faire humility,</l>
               <l>A kinde diſcretion to a dogged nature,</l>
               <l>The clowniſh race to true gentility,</l>
               <l>A bleſſed Angell to a curſed creature,</l>
               <l>Fauours to frownes, and ſmiling, vnto ſcowles,</l>
               <l>And ſay the Phoenix akes all birds but owles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4945:6"/>
               <l>Compare the earth vnto the heauen on hie,</l>
               <l>The ſpirites treaſures vnto fleſhly toies,</l>
               <l>The pibble ſtone vnto the Azurde Skie,</l>
               <l>The woes of men vnto the Angels ioyes:</l>
               <l>The loweſt weakenes vnto the higheſt powers,</l>
               <l>Then ſee the difference twixt my loue and yours.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when you ſee how all ſweete bleſsings grow</l>
               <l>But from the ground of my loues liuing grace,</l>
               <l>And do againe the imperfection know,</l>
               <l>VVherein you doe your fond affection place:</l>
               <l>Then all your titles to this truth reſigne,</l>
               <l>There is no life, but in this loue of mine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And giue me leaue to praiſe my princely Loue.</l>
               <l>Although my wittes are ſhort of ſuch a worth,</l>
               <l>And let my ſpirite in my paſsions proue,</l>
               <l>VVhat his high hand in mercy will bring forth:</l>
               <l>And write but truth that may be truly proued,</l>
               <l>My onely loue, alonely to be loued.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Before all times, al thoughts, al things he was,</l>
               <l>And euer is, and will be aye the ſame,</l>
               <l>That doth in wonder wonders wonder paſſe,</l>
               <l>In Truths high triumph of eternall fame:</l>
               <l>VVhere life, and loue, in grace and glory crownd,</l>
               <l>Do ſway the Scepter of the heauns renownd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now what he was, cannot be comprehended,</l>
               <l>VVho in himſelfe doth al things comprehend,</l>
               <l>And when that all things ſhall be wholy ended,</l>
               <l>Himſelfe, his word, his wil ſhal neuer end:</l>
               <l>Whoſe gratious life, al glorious loue beginning.</l>
               <l>Doth adde all grace, and endleſſe glory winning.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And of his Eſſence, this is al we finde,</l>
               <l>A ſpirite fully incomprehenſible,</l>
               <l>A louing God, vnto his ſeruants kind,</l>
               <l>And in his humane nature ſenſible:</l>
               <l>In wiſedomes wonder, knowledge, quinteſſence,</l>
               <l>And in that Eſſence higheſt excellence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4945:6"/>
               <l>The high Creator of al creatures liuing,</l>
               <l>The ſweet Redeemer of his ſeruants loſt,</l>
               <l>The glorious grace, all grace and glory giuing,</l>
               <l>The ioy of ioyes, that glads the ſpirit moſt:</l>
               <l>The loue of life, and life of loue indeed,</l>
               <l>Gainſt death and hell, that ſtandes the ſoule in ſteed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His ſeate is heauen, the earth his footſtoole is,</l>
               <l>His chiefeſt dwelling with his ſoules elected,</l>
               <l>His ioy to loue, and to be lou'd of his,</l>
               <l>His fauour, life, vnto his loues affected:</l>
               <l>His word is truth, which doth the ſpirit try,</l>
               <l>Where fruitfull faith ſhall liue, and neuer die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His blesſing is the peace of conſcience,</l>
               <l>His comfort mercies contemplation,</l>
               <l>His pretious gift, the ſpirites patience,</l>
               <l>His mercy, vertues meditation:</l>
               <l>His grace the oyle, that kils the ſpirits euill,</l>
               <l>His death the life, that did ſubdue the deuill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His garments are the ſundry ſortes of graces,</l>
               <l>His tribute is but ſinners ſacrifice,</l>
               <l>His worke, the planting vertues in their places,</l>
               <l>His gaine, the loue of humble ſpirits ſeruice:</l>
               <l>His muſicke Pſalmes, that angels neuer ceaſe</l>
               <l>To ſing in glory of the King of Peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This King of peace, this God of life and loue,</l>
               <l>Who in himſelfe doth al, and only holde,</l>
               <l>The higheſt blesſings of the hearts behoue,</l>
               <l>That faithful truth hath to the ſpirit tolde:</l>
               <l>This is the ſubſtance of my ſoules delight,</l>
               <l>Vnworthy ſubiect of his worth to write.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet as his mercy will vouchſafe me grace,</l>
               <l>With interceſsion of his high aſsiſtance,</l>
               <l>Againſt the power that would my thoughts deface,</l>
               <l>And proudly make againſt the ſoule reſiſtance:</l>
               <l>I will a little giue his loue a tuch,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſmalleſt praiſe is for my penne too much.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4945:7"/>
               <l>What loue was that which made him like man beſt,</l>
               <l>Of all the workes that euer he created,</l>
               <l>What loue againe did in that liking reſt,</l>
               <l>To loue him ſo he neuer can be hated:</l>
               <l>What loue was more to giue the man a wife,</l>
               <l>What loue was moſt to die to giue him life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The earth within with ſiluer gemmes and gold,</l>
               <l>Without with trees and herbs, and fruits and flowers,</l>
               <l>The waters deepe where fiſhes keepe their hold,</l>
               <l>The Elements with all their inward powers:</l>
               <l>Theſe hath my Love all made for man to chuſe,</l>
               <l>And to his pleaſure in his ſeruice vſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The fire was made to kill the chilling cold.</l>
               <l>The water made to ſlacke the burning heate,</l>
               <l>The ſubtile ayre a ſecret breath to hold,</l>
               <l>The earth to drie when moiſture is too great:</l>
               <l>Theſe croſſe in natures yet doe meete in one,</l>
               <l>Onely to ſerue the vſe of man alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Each bird, each beaſt, each foule, and euery fiſh,</l>
               <l>The fleſh of man muſt ſerue to cloath and feede,</l>
               <l>What eye can ſee, or heart of man can wiſh,</l>
               <l>But ſome way ſerues to ſtand poore men in ſteede.</l>
               <l>And for that cauſe their being firſt began.</l>
               <l>From mercies Loue, to ſerue the life of man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The light was made to glad the lightſome eie,</l>
               <l>The ſound to pleaſe the pure attentiue eare,</l>
               <l>The aire to drawe a liuing breath thereby,</l>
               <l>The earth, the body, and the limmes to beare:</l>
               <l>The clouds, the ſtars, the ſunne, the moone, the Skie,</l>
               <l>Were made for man, to make him looke on high.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All theſe were made out of the mould of Loue,</l>
               <l>Was neuer Loue came euer neere to this,</l>
               <l>Which doth a wonder in affection proue,</l>
               <l>Euen when we leaſt deſerude the loue of his:</l>
               <l>For when our ſoules did moſt offences do him,</l>
               <l>He came himſelfe in loue to call vs to him,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4945:7"/>
               <l>To make, redeeme, preſerue, defend, and cheriſh,</l>
               <l>His faithfull ſoules, and ſo in loue to nouriſh,</l>
               <l>As in his loue, their liues ſhall neuer periſh,</l>
               <l>But like the Lilly liue and euer flouriſh:</l>
               <l>Are theſe not points ſufficient to approue,</l>
               <l>The true affection of a piereleſſe Loue?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet more to ſay, that truely may be ſaid,</l>
               <l>In humble honour of this heauenly Loue,</l>
               <l>In mercies ſweete to make the ſoule diſmaide,</l>
               <l>To ſee the bleſſing of his God aboue:</l>
               <l>The louing ſpirit liuely to refreſh,</l>
               <l>He let his ſeruants ſee him in the fleſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To ſee him ſo, as might not hurt their ſight,</l>
               <l>For none might ſee his high ſupernall power,</l>
               <l>But in his loue to ſee that glorious light,</l>
               <l>That gaines that ſweete that cuts off euery ſower</l>
               <l>The ſecond perſon of himſelfe, his ſonne,</l>
               <l>In whom are all things to his glory done.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſee the cauſe why ſo he came vnto vs,</l>
               <l>His onely loue the onely cauſe we liue,</l>
               <l>And when we came, what comfort did he doe vs,</l>
               <l>To ſaue our liues, his Loue his life did giue:</l>
               <l>And ſo to ſaue vs from the fire of hell,</l>
               <l>That with his Loue we might for euer dwell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What Loue was this, to leaue his heauenly ſeate</l>
               <l>Among his angels, all in glory ſerued,</l>
               <l>To come to man who did too ill intreate</l>
               <l>The ſacred Loue, that hath his life preſerued,</l>
               <l>From being honourde, praiſde and glorifide,</l>
               <l>To be diſgraced, whipte, and crucifide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In loue he left his higheſt heauenly pleaſures,</l>
               <l>Aboue his Angels in their heapes of ioyes,</l>
               <l>To liue on earth in ſorrowes out of meaſures,</l>
               <l>With change of nothing but the worlds annoies:</l>
               <l>In toile and trauell, long in loue he ſought vs,</l>
               <l>And with his death at laſt full dearely bought vs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4945:8"/>
               <l>Oh woful trauaile that he vndertooke,</l>
               <l>To bring our liues vnto his ſacred loue,</l>
               <l>Which paine, nor croſſe, nor death it ſelfe forſooke,</l>
               <l>That to our faith might his affection proue:</l>
               <l>Which left the ſpirite of his loue behinde him,</l>
               <l>To ſhew the loue that ſeekes him, how to finde him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In loue he came, that he might comfort doe vs,</l>
               <l>In loue went from vs, to prouide our places,</l>
               <l>In loue he ſent his comforter vnto vs,</l>
               <l>In loue he guides vs with his holy graces:</l>
               <l>In loue he made, bought, keepes and guides vs thus,</l>
               <l>And ſhal not we loue him that ſo loued vs?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yes my deare Lord, be thou my deareſt loue,</l>
               <l>For Chriſt his ſake, let my ſoule neuer leaue thee.</l>
               <l>Who in thy loue, thy liuing truth doth proue,</l>
               <l>That makes me find the world doth all deceiue me:</l>
               <l>And were there truth on earth as there is none,</l>
               <l>Yet were thy loue the ioy of life alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And let theſe teares be witnes of my loue,</l>
               <l>Which firſt do begge remiſsion of my ſinne,</l>
               <l>And in repentance do but mercy moue,</l>
               <l>To ope the gates of grace and let me in:</l>
               <l>VVhere humble faith but at thy feete may fall,</l>
               <l>VVith my ſoules ſeruice, loue, and life, and all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Forget O Lord, my workes of wickednes,</l>
               <l>VVhereby my ſoule with ſorrow is oppreſſed,</l>
               <l>And with the finger of thy holines,</l>
               <l>In mercy touch my ſpirit ſo diſtreſſed:</l>
               <l>And ſaue my life that draweth nigh to hel,</l>
               <l>Loue mea little, and I ſhal be wel.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Loue? no ſweete Lord mercie I craue no more,</l>
               <l>My ſinnes are ſuch, I dare not ſpeake of loue,</l>
               <l>But in thy mercie, to thy loue reſtore</l>
               <l>My humble faith, that may but mercie proue:</l>
               <l>And ſo approue, that al the world may ſee,</l>
               <l>The ioyful loue betwixt my God and mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4945:8"/>
               <l>Oh call me home, and make me heare thy call,</l>
               <l>And heare thee ſo, that I may runne vnto thee,</l>
               <l>And hold me faſt that I may neuer fall,</l>
               <l>But that my ſoule may euer ſeruice do thee:</l>
               <l>Shew ſome good token, that the world may know,</l>
               <l>My ſoule is bleſt, whom thou haſt loued ſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And while I liue here in this wretched vale,</l>
               <l>Of feareful danger of infernal death,</l>
               <l>Where earthly pleaſures take thoſe ſoules to ſale,</l>
               <l>VVhich haue their bargaine in the hel beneath:</l>
               <l>Let my ſoules loue, and life, and labour be,</l>
               <l>To ſeeke my ioy, my loue, and life in thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Make me not rich leſt I forget to thinke,</l>
               <l>From whence I haue the comfort of my hart,</l>
               <l>Nor in ſuch want, let thy poore ſeruant ſinke,</l>
               <l>That I be driuen to craue the needy part:</l>
               <l>Giue me but meanes the needie to relieue,</l>
               <l>To feede thy flocke, and not the wolfe to grieue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let me not liſten to the ſinners ſongs,</l>
               <l>But to the Pſalmes thy holy ſaints do ſing,</l>
               <l>Nor let me folow tyrants in their wrongs,</l>
               <l>But kiſſe the rocke where righteouſnes doth ſpring:</l>
               <l>Let not mine eye affect the outward part,</l>
               <l>But let me loue the vertue of the hart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And let my loue be, to behold thy loue,</l>
               <l>And let my loue be, but to liue in thee,</l>
               <l>And ſo to liue, that al the world may proue,</l>
               <l>The gracious good my God hath done for me:</l>
               <l>To call my ſoule out of this world of woe,</l>
               <l>In faithful loue to ſerue my Sauiour ſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when they ſee the blot of al their blame,</l>
               <l>To loue the world, but al in wretched toyes,</l>
               <l>And do confeſſe with inward bluſhing ſhame,</l>
               <l>They are but ſorrowes vnto heauenly ioyes:</l>
               <l>They may with me forſake al worldly pleaſure,</l>
               <l>And make thy loue an euerlaſting treaſure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4945:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>For Lord by thee we are, in thee we liue.</l>
               <l>And in thy loue the liuing cannot die,</l>
               <l>And ſince thy death did our liues wholly giue,</l>
               <l>For thy loues ſake ſhall we affection flie?</l>
               <l>No my deare Lord, let life be death to me,</l>
               <l>So I may die to liue in loue with thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A ioyfull life were ſuch a death indeede,</l>
               <l>From earthly paine to paſſe to heauenly pleaſure,</l>
               <l>A ioyfull line for louing hearts to reade,</l>
               <l>To leaue the fleſh, to take the ſpirits treaſure:</l>
               <l>Whoſe glorious ſence vnto the ſunne doth fall,</l>
               <l>That all is nothing to that all in all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And I (alas) of many thouſand ſoules,</l>
               <l>Vnworthie moſt of his high worth to write,</l>
               <l>Who in his mercies true record inrowles</l>
               <l>The louing ſubſtance of the ſoules delight,</l>
               <l>Muſt mercie crie, for feare my loues preſuming</l>
               <l>Of too high ſence, may be my ſoules conſuming.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And with the teares of true repentant loue,</l>
               <l>Looking vppon the wonders of that wonder,</l>
               <l>That in his leaſt perfection may approue</l>
               <l>The greateſt wiſdome of the world put vnder,</l>
               <l>Confeſſe my wit as ſhort to penne his prayſe,</l>
               <l>As darkeſt nights in light of cleareſt daies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſay but this in grace and glories height,</l>
               <l>Where vertues loue doth liue for euer crowned,</l>
               <l>And all the Hoaſt of heauen and heauens await,</l>
               <l>Vpon the higheſt of the heauens renowned:</l>
               <l>Whom Saints and Angels trembling do adore,</l>
               <l>To him alone be praiſe for euermore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If honour praiſe and glory euer bee,</l>
               <l>Vnto my louing euerlaſting King,</l>
               <l>This King of life who ſo hath loued me,</l>
               <l>To giue my ſoule this gratious power to ſing:</l>
               <l>In heart and minde, in man and Angels loue,</l>
               <l>All glorious glory be to God aboue.</l>
            </lg>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Nicholas Britton.</hi>
            </bibl>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4945:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
